<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-08-14T06:35:32+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title>agency</title><subtitle>Codiators - web agency.</subtitle><author><name>{&quot;name&quot;=&gt;nil, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;nil, &quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;nil}</name></author><entry><title>On-board Coding Blog 2</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/04/27/on-board-coding-blog-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On-board Coding Blog 2" /><published>2017-04-27T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2017-04-27T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2017/04/27/on-board-coding-blog-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2017/04/27/on-board-coding-blog-2/">&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the second web development blog/tutorial.This blog will highlight the essential skills required for becoming a good full-stack developer(emphasizing on the word “good”). Also covered are the resources(videos,courses,tutorials,articles,etc.) that will help you in acquiring
these skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full-stack development is much more than just front-end and back-end.There are various technologies that are as essential as programming,in order to develop good web applications.The purpose of this tutorial is to open the pandora’s box of the world of web development and introduce to you the skills that a full-stack developer should have.Read them and try to follow up on the resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just keep in mind that these skills are to be acquired over a considerable period of time and with a lot of experience.Don’t expect to learn them in a hurry.Most of these skills will be automatically acquired once you start developing applications for yourself or for a company like ours(CODIATORS).However,it is necessary to present to you the entire stack of web development(the stack in full-stack development).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as our(codiators’) requirements are concerned you are expected to learn atleast one technology(one for front-end and one for back-end) with basic version control(eg. git)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this blog we will highlight the skills a full-stack developer must have(don’t be
overwhelmed!).And we will tell you which skill or part of the skill you should focus on.Happy learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following are the main technology stacks required for full-stack development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;system-administration&quot;&gt;System Administration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;System administration refers to the management of one or more hardware and software
systems.Our application/s will be hosted on a server and we need someone to oversee the management of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This task is performed by a system administrator who monitors system health, monitors and allocates system resources like disk space, performs backups, provides user access, manages user accounts, monitors system security and performs many other functions.
This skill requires the following sub-skills:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Linux and basic shell scripting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cloud computing: Amazon, Rackspace, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Background processing: Gearman, Redis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Search: Elasticsearch, Sphinx, Solr&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Caching: Varnish, Memcached, APC / OpCache&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Monitoring: Nagios&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of now your focus should be to learn linux and basic shell scripting.Linux powers most of the internet.Most of the web apps are hosted on linux run servers.Shell scripting is a way to communicate with the server(running linux) using commands.Hence learning shell scripting is crucial for a system administrator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following is the standard resource that will help you understand shell scripting and make you learn the same&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.freeos.com/guides/lsst/&quot;&gt;Linux and shell scripting tutorial&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;web-development-tools&quot;&gt;Web development tools&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Version control: Git, Mercurial, SVN&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Virtualization: VirtualBox, Vagrant, Docker&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The version control should be your focus area.Version control is a system that records changes to a file or set of files over time so that you can recall specific versions later. Refer the following link and read more about version control and it’s importance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://oss-watch.ac.uk/resources/versioncontrol&quot;&gt;Version Control and its Importance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Git is the standard version control system used by most developers across the world.Git (/ɡɪt/) is a version control system (VCS) for tracking changes in computer files and coordinating work on those files among multiple people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow the link below and learn git.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://try.github.io/levels/1/challenges/1&quot;&gt;Learn git in 15 minutes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now leavle earning virtualization.It’s one of those skills that will be acquired as you become a developer in some organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pre-requisites-for-web-development&quot;&gt;Pre-requisites For web-development&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now before introducing the back-end and front-end technologies, you need to setup your system with essential tools and software installations for practicing and developing web applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Operating System
The operating system may not sound like an important thing to set up.But ask any
developer about their preferred OS and they all will recommend using Linux Distros.Linux OS’s come with developer friendly features and are therefore used widely by the developer community.Also they are free and OpenSource.Personally I recommend installing Ubuntu from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ubuntu.com/download/desktop&quot;&gt;Ubuntu Download&lt;/a&gt;.Install the same by following these &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ubuntu.com/download/desktop/install-ubuntu-desktop&quot;&gt;steps&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Developer tools
The place where you write the code can depend on your choice.Various options are available to do the same.You can go for IDE’s(Integrated development environment) or you can choose the text editors.IDE’s will allow you a lot of benefits like writing the code,compiling the code and debugging all in the same place.Choosing which IDE to use depends on the language support you need.Because we will be focussing on RubyOnRails we prefer you to use editors.
There are many text editors available such as Atom,Sublime,TextMate,etc.Choose any
according to your system and install accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ruby and Rails Install
We will essentially want you to focus on learning ruby and rails.To start working on these you will require to install them on your system.
Follow the steps in this &lt;a href=&quot;http://railsapps.github.io/installrubyonrails-ubuntu.html&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; to install ruby and rails with rvm(ruby version manager).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;back-end-tech&quot;&gt;Back-end Tech&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This ​is one of the most important part of a software application.This is the submerged part of the iceberg,which users of the application do not get to see.Also most programming happens in this part.Out of all the skills required to become a full-stack developer this is the single biggest skill.This will also take the maximum learning time.So don’t worry if you spend a few months
learning and mastering it.Learn this skill well enough and increase your chances of landing a job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following is the list of tech that is part of back-end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Web servers: Apache, Nginx&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Programming language: PHP, NodeJS, Ruby&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Database: MySQL, PostgreSQL,MongoDB, Cassandra, Redis, SQL / JSON in general&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The web servers are the software that hosts the web applications.Apache and Nginx are two ofthe most popular web server software available.
PHP is the by far the most used programming language on the back-end side.However we recommend learning ruby first.Ruby language has a focus on simplicity and productivity.That is,it is easier to learn and understand(simplicity) and it is faster to develop web applications(productivity).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ruby on Rails(RoR) is a popular framework for web development written in ruby.It is supported by a large community and has many ruby gems available which aids developing web applications.The gems are useful ruby programs which a developer can install in his/her application without having to write a single line of code himself/herself.A lot of common web functionalities are available as gems.This speeds up the development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start learning ruby first and then shift to learning RoR:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Free Ruby Course&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For learning Ruby on Rails,refer the book Ruby On Rails Tutorial(Michael Hartl)
This will take a lot of time and effort.Persist through it,follow the tutorials and practice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;front-end-tech&quot;&gt;Front-end Tech&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The front-end part is what the user gets to see and interact with.To make your application look good and behave good,you will need to learn the following technologies:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;HTML / HTML5: Semantic web&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CSS / CSS3: LESS, SASS, Media Queries&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;JavaScript: jQuery, AngularJS, Knockout, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Compatibility quirks across browsers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Responsive design&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AJAX, JSON, XML, WebSocket&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again no need to learn everything right now.Just put your focus on learning HTML5,CSS3 and some Javascript. HTML and CSS will design your web page layout and make it look good.Javascript will make your application behave well.The interaction made by the user and the corresponding changes on the website are made possible by javascript.Also javascript is the MOST important of all the
languages,because knowing only javascript you will be able to develop an entire application from front-end to back-en(MEAN stack).This MEAN stack is entirely based on javascript.So learning javascript along with HTML and CSS is very crucial.Follow the given resources for learning these technologies and try to practice them a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For HTML and CSS:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.codecademy.com/learn/web&quot;&gt;Codecademy HTML and CSS course&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rithmschool.com/courses/html-css-fundamentals&quot;&gt;Rithm school free course on HTML and CSS (optional)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rithmschool.com/courses/intermediate-css-bootstrap&quot;&gt;Advanced CSS and Twitter Bootstrap course (optional)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://marksheet.io/&quot;&gt;Marksheet.io (optional)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Javascript:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.codecademy.com/&quot;&gt;Javascript basic codecademy course&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rithmschool.com/courses/javascript&quot;&gt;Rithm school Javascript fundamentals course (optional but highly recommended &amp;amp; personally my favorite)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have tried our best to give you the references that will help you in becoming a full-stack developer.Let us know about your views on the blogs or if there are any better resources available on the same by commenting below or sending us an
email(sulaythakkar9@gmail.com).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>{&quot;name&quot;=&gt;nil, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;nil, &quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;nil}</name></author><summary>Welcome to the second web development blog/tutorial.This blog will highlight the essential skills required for becoming a good full-stack developer(emphasizing on the word “good”). Also covered are the resources(videos,courses,tutorials,articles,etc.) that will help you in acquiring
these skills.</summary></entry><entry><title>On-board Coding Blog 1</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/04/27/on-board-coding-blog-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On-board Coding Blog 1" /><published>2017-04-27T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2017-04-27T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2017/04/27/on-board-coding-blog-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2017/04/27/on-board-coding-blog-1/">&lt;p&gt;Hello guys,this is an introductory coding blog/tutorial about the web development for those guys that want to join CODIATORS as web developers. Our expectation about the people that want to work with us as web developers,is that they go through these blogs,do as asked and then contact(sulaythakkar9@gmail.com) us.This will make working with us faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However,it should be also helpful to those who simply want to get a heads-up about web-development in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These blogs are not just to cultivate an understanding about the nitty-gritty of web development but also to help the reader build the applications from scratch.This process is covered in blog#3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-web-development&quot;&gt;What is web development?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Web development​ broadly refers to the tasks associated with developing​ websites for hosting via intranet or Internet. The Web development​ process includes Web​design, Web​ content development​, client-side/server-side scripting and network security configuration, among other
tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.techopedia.com/definition/23889/web-development&quot;&gt;Web Development defination&lt;/a&gt;: Techopedia&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-full-stack-development&quot;&gt;What is full-stack development?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we understand the full-stack development,we need to understand the terms Back-end
and Front-end first.(Refer the image)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/web-delopment.png&quot; alt=&quot;Full-stack development&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;front-end&quot;&gt;Front-end&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Front​-end​ web development​, also known as client-side development​ is the practice of
producing HTML, CSS and JavaScript for a website or Web Application so that a user can see and interact with them directly.This side of programming deals with what the user gets to see on the browser,as shown in the above image.(Note: HTML,CSS,Javascript are some well-known front-end languages.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The web browser actually interprets the source code,and then renders it for display.Most web browsers today,can only interpret HTML,CSS,Javascript languages.So as far as the front-end is concerned these are the only languages required to be learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;back-end&quot;&gt;Back-end&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Software applications are like icebergs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a portion of the application the user sees(front-end) and then—in most cases—the largest part of the application remains unseen. This is the elusive and mystical “back-end”. Most part of the code that gets written for any web application is the back-end code,that does not translate into user interaction code(i.e the visual stuff).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This includes the storing and retrieving of data from a database,performing some logic on the data and calculating the results.PHP,Ruby and Python are some of the most used back-end(server-side) 
programming languages.&lt;a href=&quot;https://simpleprogrammer.com/2016/12/12/what-is-back-end-development/&quot;&gt;What is back-end development&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-are-databases&quot;&gt;What are databases?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Databases are basically containers for data.This data is information about the users of the application,and other system related data.There are various types of databases,just like we have different languages for front-end and back-end development.The basic purpose of all these databases,is to store data and allow retrieval of data when requested.We choose the type of database according to our data requirements.More on this in the second blog/tutorial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we can understand the term full-stack development.The term full-stack developer means
developers who are comfortable working with both back-end and front-end technologies.
To be more specific, it means that the developer can work with databases, PHP, HTML, CSS,
JavaScript and everything in between, also, venturing as far as converting Photoshop designs to front-end code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A full-stack developer doesn’t need to master all of the areas and technologies he needs to work at, because that just makes it nearly impossible, he just needs to be comfortable working with those technologies, and that’s a lot too.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sitepoint.com/full-stack-developer/&quot;&gt;Being a full-stack developer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This covers the introduction part for the full-stack web development.Check out
the On-board coding tutorial blog#2 for the skills required to become a good
full-stack web developer and how to acquire them.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>{&quot;name&quot;=&gt;nil, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;nil, &quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;nil}</name></author><summary>Hello guys,this is an introductory coding blog/tutorial about the web development for those guys that want to join CODIATORS as web developers. Our expectation about the people that want to work with us as web developers,is that they go through these blogs,do as asked and then contact(sulaythakkar9@gmail.com) us.This will make working with us faster.</summary></entry></feed>
